[Music]
all right hello and welcome to active
inference model stream number 13.1 it's
August 23rd 2024 we're here with two of
the authors of the paper synthesizing
the born rule with reinforcement
learning so thank you both for joining
for this presentation and discussion to
you Jo for the presentation
great thanks for inviting me Daniel um
and yeah it's really fun to learn about
the the AC of inference Community um and
to speak to you guys so I think there'll
be as many questions from us to
you uh as there will be from you guys to
us um so I'm not going to take up too
much time I hope with my slides um I
wanted to just give a kind of high level
overview of this article which
hopefully um many of you have already
had time to look over but I'll give you
a high level overview and um that
shouldn't take more than about 30
minutes I guess and after that we'll
have plenty of time for discussion um
there will be many points where you
might feel that you want more
information uh more more technical
details but since I couldn't really
predict which points might strike you as
the most interesting I'll leave it to
you to ask at the end and uh as
necessary I might um be able to pull up
the article and point the relevant Parts
yeah uh let's dive into it oh and and
one last thing you you might hear some
background noises of either drilling or
a baby
screaming that's just uh because I'm at
home at the moment and uh it's part of
the domestic
atmosphere okay let's go
so this is um a very busy slide sorry
for that but we do have a lot of people
involved in this from many different
institutions I'll I'll put this slide
also at the end of the talk um in case
you're curious but it's it's important
to mention um we you we've got five
people based at
the uh Institute of physics uh in lab Q
Rio Rio de Janeiro and that that's where
I'm currently
based although before this I was was uh
where you know during the time that this
paper was mostly written I was at the
University of Massachusetts Boston
together uh with um two other co-authors
on this paper are from there as well and
we're all part of the cubism
group uh run by Chris fuks so I'll I'll
speak a little bit about cubism um which
is an interpretation of quantum theory
based on subjective basion decision
Theory a bit of mouthful but if you're
curious about that we can talk about it
more at the end uh and John has since
gone on to um uh the University of New
Mexico and the the lead author of this
work is Rodrigo Pio who was a PhD
student at the time of this work and
he's now at the Technology Innovation
Institute in Abu
[Music]
Dhabi so this is another paper that was
published um some years ago now just
during the pandemic or towards the end
of the
pandemic um and this was by us at the
cubism group so you can see John and I
are there uh Chris fuks is there um this
was a purely theoretical paper but it
contains the seeds for for the article
that I'm going to talk about so I'm
going to just take a little diversion to
explain what we did in this paper
as a a
motivation for the article that I'll
talk
about here's a little exop from from the
abstract the the title of the paper is
born's Rule as a Quantum extension of
basion
coherence and explaining that a little
bit uh from the abstract the subjective
vasion interpretation of quantum
mechanics that we calling
cubism asserts that the born rule rule
is a normative rule in analogy to Dutch
book coherence I'll explain what born
Rule and and Dutch book coherence are
don't worry uh but with the addition of
one or more empirical assumptions
characterizing the particularities of
the physical
world so the idea is that we're taking
this rule called the born rule from
quantum
physics and we're saying that you can
understand that rule as coming from
decision
Theory this prision Theory
plus certain empirical
assumptions okay so let let me explain
what what that
means bit of
terminology what is this interpretation
the subje evasion interpretation of
quantum theory well there's a lot I
could say about it but for for the
purposes of this paper
decision theory in other words the
theory of agents who
are uh trying their best to make good
decisions in the world and they use
probability theory in order to do
that and quantum theory takes into
account certain empirical facts things
that we've learned from experiments and
uh gives us an upgrade to our decision
Theory and that's what we call quantum
mechanics according to
[Music]
cubism and when I talk about bn's rule
you might have come across it in what
I'm calling the Legacy form it's the
rule that tells you when you have some
Quantum State and you do a measurement
on it which traditionally is an
observable that has some set of igen
States uh labeled with I've just labeled
them abstractly with an index J I'm
assuming a discrete Spectrum here uh
then to find out the probability for
getting some outcome J uh you you just
have to uh take the
overlap of the quantum state with the
relevant igen projector and you take the
modulus squared of that to give you a
positive real number and that's the
probability but nowadays uh We've
generalized the rule so
from uh the the literature on open
systems and information Theory
uh we have accommodated more General
measurements so you don't just have to
measure observables which are uh which
kind of project you into an igen basis
uh where each projector is orthogonal to
the other ones uh you have these things
called um positive operator value
measures which is a horrible name we
just call them povms and everyone even
forgets what they stand for um but you
can basically think about them as uh a
general generalization of of um
observables they're the most General
thing the general most General kind of
measurement you could possibly do in
quantum theory so that's what that D
subscript J stands for uh it's it's an
element corresponding to outcome J of
the most General Quantum measurement and
then in that case the quantum state is
represented by a density Matrix which is
that little Greek letter row under the
trace
and if you take the trace of the state
with the povm element DJ then that will
give you the probability for the outcome
J in that Quantum State
row um I hope that's familiar to to at
least some people watching this but if
not feel free to quiz us on it it's not
super important to the rest of the talk
though the important thing is bn's rule
is is a you can think of it like um a
piece of the Machinery of quantum
mechanics that takes your Quantum State
and measurement and as input and it
outputs the probability that you should
assign uh for for each
outcome so it's a very important piece
of the quantum
formalism and what we found in this old
in this paper which is the motivation
for all of this is the following imagine
that you have a perfectly rational
decision making agent okay per perfectly
rational agents don't exist in reality
but they're they're useful to
contemplate in the
abstract uh and by perfectly rational I
I just mean that
uh it it respects the the basic laws of
probability Theory so it it assigns
probabilities
to events which add up to one for a
complete mutually exclusive set of
events that the probabilities are
positive between 01 and so forth um and
in particular it assigns probabilities
in a in a consistent
way um and I'll explain a bit more what
that means so suppose this agent is
placing bets on the outcomes of
measurements on some physical
system and we're going to assume that
they hold certain beliefs about how the
system responds to those measurements
the first set of
beliefs uh again this is a high level if
if you want to know the actual
assumptions you'll have to look at the
paper um or ask me about it afterwards
but there's a set of assumptions that
are generic so they they are things we
would expect to hold in any physical
Theory and they include things like the
possibility of State tomography in other
words uh you should be able to
reconstruct the physical state of the
system by doing a sufficiently complete
measurement on it and looking at the
statistics of the
outcomes uh and maximality is just a
principle we use use in any situation
where there's ambiguity about how to
choose things we will just uh use a
maximality principle which kind of uh
assumes the least structure necessary uh
in order to draw conclusions you could
also call it a minimality assumption I
mean these things can always be flipped
around it's a kind of all else being
equal assumption so generic stuff but
then there there's um an empiric
inspired I call it a Proto Quantum
assumption why Proto Quantum because
this assumption actually itself is not
sufficient uh to imply quantum
theory but it it's also something which
you would not expect to hold in a
classical
Theory um so it's kind of this is the
key assumption which which takes us
outside of the domain of classical
physics and takes a first step in the
direction of of quantum theory without
presuming the full Quantum
formalism and this assumption is defined
purely at the level at the operational
level so you can using information
Theory uh you can consider things like
how much data can I reliably store and
retrieve in my
system uh and that gives you a concept
that I'll call the informational
dimension of your system so you know if
you have a Quantum bit for example
um even though a Quantum bit is in a
certain sense more informationally Rich
than than a classical bit ultimately you
can only store a single classical bit of
information in a way that can be
reliably you know perfectly encoded and
retrieved uh so that the informational
dimension of a of a classical bit and a
qbit is
two uh but then there's another concept
of Dimension which this this is not
conventional usage of this term but I
find it convenient I call the the
tomographic
dimension uh which basically says
remember I'm I'm assuming State
tomography so there's some there's some
measurement you could do on the system
this is an assumption such that if you
knew the statistics for the measurement
outcomes you could perfectly
reconstruct what the state of the system
was and then you can ask a question well
what's the minimum number of outcomes
which that measurement needs to have so
that's what I'm calling the tomographic
Dimension and essentially our our Proto
Quantum assumption is that the
tomographic dimension is equal to the
square of the informational
Dimension uh I know that's a lot to take
in um if you want we can come back to it
it's not super important for what
follows but I thought it's worth
mentioning that this assumption is is
inspired by experiment there's no reason
why out of the blue somebody would
believe that this should be true
in fact in classical physics it's not
true classically the tomographic
dimension is exactly equal to the
informational
Dimension um so the only reasons an
agent would believe in this particular
assumption um would be because of uh
trying to explain statistics which we
have from measuring Quantum systems
among other
reasons and our main finding in this old
paper is
that if the
agent assigns their probabilities
according to these two sets of
assumptions then on pain of
inconsistency in other words in order to
be perfectly rational and consistent
they would have to assign their
probabilities according to the born rule
so even though we haven't assumed the
mathematical formalism of quantum theory
we have found that just a a
minimal non-class IAL assumption is
already enough to get you the the born
rule exactly the the quantum born
rule um so that's quite interesting I I
mentioned here a Dutch book if you're
wondering what that is it's from the
it's part of what we mean by a rational
agent in the basian literature a Dutch
book is a series of bets uh which the
agent would agree to anyone taken
individually but if you consider them
together uh they would um be irrational
to accept so it's kind of a litmus test
for whether an agent's beliefs are uh
internally
consistent the point is just that the
agent would be irrational unless they
use the born rule in this case so what
what does this mean what's the upshot of
this
result well putting it in context it's
important to emphasize that this is the
first time that I know of um that the
born rule is derived from essentially
pure decision Theory you know plus some
pretty minimal empirical assumptions
without
presupposing uh the quantum mechanical
formalism by which I mean things like
Hilbert spaces unary maps and so on you
know complex numbers all of that
previously in the literature the born
rule has been assumed as an
axiom um just
posited uh that was how it was first
introduced by Max borne
himself um and there have been attempts
to derive it from decision Theory but
they usually need to
invoke uh some of the formal structure
of quantum mechanics such as unitary
Dynamics um so so we've really made
significant progress compared to that
literature but I think the deeper point
is that this shows that born's rule is
far more Universal than quantum
theory um it actually applies in a range
of settings where your theory might not
be quantum theory it might be some more
general theory that's just not
classical um and it it really just stems
from some fairly basic assumptions about
what the agent uh believes about the
system uh and and you could say one
conclusion to draw from this is that a
perfectly rational agent who has the
right kind of perceptual apparatus you
know in order for them to see these
empirical Quantum effects in the right
kind of
environment uh would be uh well would
would essentially be forced to use
born's rule to to make their decisions
well that's
nice uh and it got us thinking just how
Universal is it so we we've been talking
about rational agents who explicitly
make decisions using probability Theory
that's pretty Advanced for an agent that
means that they they can think they can
reason explicitly they they have minds
and Consciousness and not just
Consciousness but mathematics formal
mathematics you know they can write down
probabilities and so on and we were
wondering well but this the elements
here are so simple that it seems like
you might not even need that much
firstly what if the agent wasn't
perfectly rational there's a lot of
literature studying uh deviations from
perfect r nationality in uh in conscious
reasoning agents which is super
interesting but we went to an even more
basic level with and we were kind of
inspired by the the act of inference the
ant colony
paper um which which is why we cited it
in that work um because that that work
kind of inspired us to wonder whether
simple organisms like ants which
definitely don't have any explicit
representation of of mathematics are
nevertheless able to behave in a way
which conforms to some fairly
sophisticated abstract
rules um so we set out to discover
whether a a really simple simulation of
an
agent um could end up behaving in a way
that that would conform to the the
quantum born rule without having any
explicit knowledge of quantum theory or
even being able to explicitly use
probabilities so in order
to uh
actually carry out this
research there's a lot of things that
one has to decide so there are so many
ways that you might think of modeling
the simple
agent and uh you know to say nothing of
the question of how to model the
environment so I'll talk about both of
those in
turn first of all we want our agent to
be ignorant of quantum mechanics as I
said uh but it's it's survival or or
there should be some uh
success parameter which depends on how
well it's able to predict the outcome of
a measurement on some Quantum system the
idea being that that it's through it's
me ments on on Quantum systems that it
will ensure its own Survival and that's
why it will ultimately we hope learn to
behave in a way that respects the the
born
Rule and so our agent will um learn from
its
experience and to do that we we'll use a
kind of action response feedback loop so
at each moment the agent will place bets
in which it it kind of tries to get the
probability for some uh outcome to occur
and then depending on what happens and
what the actual outcome is it will get
some uh reward SL
penalty uh and that will then cause it
to adjust Its Behavior for future
betting and we made some additional
simplifying
assumptions we we really wanted to start
with the the simplest thing we could
possibly think of just as a as a
preliminary
test um and in many ways
we uh perhaps
oversimplified but um we also did quite
a lot to you know even though our our
algorithm you'll see is not very
sophisticated um we also helped it quite
a lot in other ways so I'll explain that
so we assume firstly that it's Marian in
other words the decision it makes at any
given moment um should only depend on on
the average um expected reward for for
each of the possible actions it could
take um so it doesn't remember exactly
the sequence of rewards that it obtained
for a given action it just remembers the
relative um the the average expected
reward for each one
um so you know it kind of has a memory
just just in terms of its state at a
given time but that state only keeps the
information
of the relative
weightings um and I call it a Proto
basion agent it can't be aasan agent
because it's not using probability
Theory it's just reacting in a kind of a
dumb uh simplistic way but it's Proto
agent in the sense that if you give it
enough data so if you take the limit as
um as the data goes to
Infinity uh you want to find that it
will behave
exactly the same way that an intelligent
conscious rational basan agent would um
so that that would kind of be the limit
of of um you know the limit of large
data corresponds to the limit of perfect
rationality and when you look to lower
amounts of data you can think of that as
a weakening of perfect rationality due
to the finite resources of the agent and
that's what we wanted to investigate
what happens when you go to smaller
amounts of data which which is what you
would expect for um a real organism
can't sit around collecting data um you
know without paying some kind of cost it
doesn't have infinite time or or
energy and uh a very natural way to
implement this kind of algorithm is a
reinforcement learning
algorithm and uh this is a sketch of how
it
runs um in our implementation so at each
step
s and for each possible outcome J of of
whatever measurement we consider I'll
get to that um the agent has to choose a
bet b of J from a discrete set of n
options uh which take values in the
interval between zero and one so the
idea here is that the agents when in
choosing a bet um they are guessing what
the what essentially what the
probability is for the outcome J of
course they don't use probabilities
explicitly for the agent this is just an
action the prob you know the the reason
for us putting it in this interval is
because we know as Outsiders that at the
level of analysis these things will in
the limit of large uh step large numbers
of steps s um these bets should
correspond exactly to probabilities
um but it's from the agent's point of
view if you like this is just a discrete
set of n possible actions that it could
take and that's really all it means to
the
agent and there is an interesting issue
here because you would say well if these
things are supposed to correspond to
bets on probabilities we're kind of
fundamentally limiting the agents um
because we're not allowing them to pick
any real number between zero and one and
that's an interesting point um we had to
do that because you can imagine that if
if the agent were allowed to pick any
real number and they would start would
say a uniform prior uh on the unit
interval then they would never actually
choose the same action more than once
the probability would be um vanishingly
small that they would ever repeat an
action and an agent that behaves like
that just has no hope of surviving I
mean or you know you can't really work
with that so it's important that the
agent is able to repeatedly choose the
same action so that they can learn what
kind of responses they get there might
be more sophisticated ways to deal with
this uh but we found that actually
Beyond a certain threshold of the the
number of choices n the value of n
doesn't matter um so as long as you have
kind of a fine enough splitting up of
the interval that gets you you know
approxim close to whatever probabilities
you want to give uh it works well
enough so the agent chooses the BET and
uh then the measurement happens so again
I'll discuss the implementation of the
measurement next but the measurement
results in some
outcome which which I'm calling J
Prime and then we check whether the
current outcome that we're making bets
on is equal to J Prime and we Define
this parameter e so e is one if we're
looking at J Prime and zero if we're not
and then the reward is basically just
the difference uh between the agent's
bet and E which is 0
one um and in and and you take that to
the square and subtract it so why do you
do that this is called the quadratic
loss
function um and the usual motivation is
that this is um the reward function
which guarantees that if if you were
actually a evasion rational agent
assigning probabilities
explicitly this reward function
guarantees that uh the bets that you
place uh will match your um subjective
probability assignments so again this
comes from our demand that the agent be
a Proto basan agent basically using this
reward function guarantees that in the
the limit of many steps the relative uh
the weightings that the agent assigns to
to the the bets that it chooses will
correspond exactly to the the actual
probabilities for the outcomes so that's
why we picked it also because it it is
mathematically the simplest possible um
uh reward function it yeah I mean it I
call it a reward function but it's
negative reward so it's actually a loss
function technically and the agent is
just going to optimize that to try to
minimize its
losses and um so okay how does the agent
do that what what strategy does it use
now it's made a bed um some outcome
happens and and it receives some
feedback how does it then choose uh what
to do on the next um on the next
step and we use a pretty standard
algorithm for that called an Epsilon
greedy
algorithm basically there's some
parameter Epsilon which is supposed to
be
small um meaning significantly smaller
than
one uh but not infinite tmal you you can
kind of play around to make it what you
want and with probability
Epsilon uh the agent just chooses
randomly so it kind of
just chooses you know to see what will
happen without any particular reason but
then most of the time probability one
minus Epson it will go with the safe bet
so it'll pick the action which in the
past has given it the highest return and
this is a pretty intuitive algorithm
when you're thinking about actual
organisms
because uh you know if you just imagine
in everyday life you're picking what
restaurant to go to is a classic
example some of the time you want to um
you want to just go with a safe bet you
know the restaurant which you've been to
before and you know that it's good but
if you were to just do that you would
never actually uh find potentially
better restaurants so sometimes it's
worth taking a risk and just trying a
random new restaurant just to see if uh
you know there might be something better
out there so there this is a classic you
know uh exploration versus exploitation
balance and and the parameter Epsilon 2
how much the agent favors one or the
other and again it's a very natural
thing to pick in the context of models
of actual uh
organisms so finally let's talk about
the environment because this is in a way
where the action happens if our agent is
going to have any hope of learning to
behave in a way that's sensitive to
Quantum Mechanics you know at least that
conforms to the born rule then there has
to be something special about the
environment um if if we just put it
dumped it in in a thermal bath or you
know in some environment that could be
perfectly explained by some classical
physical model there would be no reason
to expect the agent uh to behave in a
way that follows the born rule because
the born rule is inherently a
non-classical uh you know it's applies
out inside the domain of classical
experimental physics so what what do we
need uh for our environment to to have
that sufficiently rich
structure basically we need to make sure
that the measurement statistics whatever
measurement we pick on on a Quantum
system has to be a rich enough
measurement that it
exhibits um Quantum structure well it
has to exhibit enough structure that it
can't be explained classically by some
classical model of the
environment and that led us to use
something called an informationally
complete uh Quantum
measurement you know
povm um and you you also need to
consider states of the system that are
being measured you need a variety of
different environmental States and that
also should be informationally complete
um so together this is often called a
tomographically complete set uh because
the idea is that if you know the
statistics for for the measurements for
all of these states uh you can
reconstruct the mathematical form of the
quantum state so it's kind of a safe bet
if you have an informationally complete
measurement and and set of States you
can be sure that the structure of
quantum theory is represented within the
statistics now this may be a stronger
assumption than we needed to make but as
I said it's definitely sufficient
um and this is one of the ways that we
helped out our agent made their life
easier because
realistically um you know we we don't
make any claim that uh an hypothetical
agent that was evolving in in a Quantum
environment would actually be doing this
kind of measurement um and indeed it's
not even clear what what that would even
mean you know what kind of measurements
they would be doing so we're just
avoiding that whole
um Thicket of questions and just saying
okay let's just do whatever would make
it easiest for the
agent and we we go even a little bit
further to just to simplify our own
lives as well uh we assume that this
measurement has a certain mathematical
symmetry property uh it's what they call
symmetric information complete povm we
like to call it a seek SI I please don't
call it a
sick um they're really interesting
mathematical objects um John knows all
about them and I'm sure we'll would be
happy to tell you anything you want to
know um but for our purposes what what's
great about them is that they really
simplify the form of our
equations
um and it turns out that at least in in
the lowest number of Dimensions where
this is interesting you can actually
Implement them experimentally which I'll
talk about
soon um so in this article we actually
didn't do an experiment we just proposed
one uh we did a simulation and that's
another way in which we made life easier
for the agent because in a
simulation uh you can assume that your
um Quantum states are exactly what you
want them to be you know pure States no
noise U measurements you can assume are
perfect
and again realistically If This Were an
organism the kinds of measurements it
would be doing would be completely messy
the kind of States describing the
variant would not be pure States they
would be thermal they would be
mixed um again we're just Sid stepping
that and saying let's just see what what
makes it easiest for the agent even in
that best case scenario how well would
the agent
perform uh in a simulation and you know
we can propose an experiment to kind of
see how that would play out
I wanted to just show you this slide to
give you an idea what it would look like
to do a symmetric information complete
measurement in the
lab um so so this is um something that
they can do here in
Rio um actually have done um it's a
really neat way of
implementing uh this kind of um actually
not just the metric but any uh kind of
for outcome povm
so this is an apparatus called a
displaced sagak interferometer in
Quantum Optics um the idea is that you
um so that's a laser beam going through
there that well it's actually not laser
it's the path of a single Photon that's
coming from um spontaneous parametric
down conversion which produces pairs of
entangled photons and you send one
Photon into this apparatus following
that that red line
uh and the other one uh goes to detector
which will um indicate whether it's
partner photon is present that's
important because it's a spontaneous
process you don't actually know when
there's a photon in there unless you
grab the partner Photon so the presence
of the partner Photon tells you yep now
there's a photon in the apparatus okay
so the other Photon goes into this
complicated looking thing um I won't
walk you through it but you can see
there that there are four different
output ports which label the four
possible outcomes so here we're talking
about um a dimension A system that has
informational Dimension
two uh but it has tomographic Dimension
four and since the seek is information
complete it needs to have four
outcomes um the reason that it its uh
informational Dimension is two is
because here we're using essentially as
a cubit we're using the polarization
degrees of of the single Photon so that
Photon will go in there and it'll pop
out at one of these four detectors and
depending which one it pops out at that
gives you the outcome of your
measurement and the the quantum system
which is kind of representing the states
of our environment is the single Photon
itself which can be in different Quantum
superpositions of
polarization so it's a very
contrived uh implementation but again
it's like the simplest thing you might
possibly consider and you can imagine
that your agent somehow depends on its
livelihood depends on predicting where
these photons will where where the
photon will pop out in each in each step
so every time you send a photon through
uh the agent tries to bet on the
likelihood that it will pop out at each
of these ports and every time it um you
know the the Photon pops out somewhere
then depending on what bets the agent
plac they will get rewarded
accordingly um so this is how one you
know could implement
this um now we ran our simulation and we
we simulated exactly that
setup um as a kind of Prelude to to see
what we should expect and we had a
working hypothesis going in um which is
that the agent should learn the B rule
fairly easily and our reasoning was that
we've gone through a lot of trouble to
make this experiment you know this
proposal as ideal as possible you know
we're assuming pure States perfect
measurements and so on so how hard can
it be you know this is like the most
Quantum thing that you could possibly do
uh in dimension two you cannot get more
Quantum than this um if if you like it's
like you're saying this is an
environment where we we've dialed up the
quantumness to maximum um so come on it
can't be that hard but it turns out it
is pretty hard for the agent to learn to
behave according to the born rule in
other
words um if you do an analysis of its
betting
strategy um you can measure how close
its betting strategy is to the to the
quantum rule the born rule um there
there's a bit of math involved in how
you do that comparison but basically uh
you can formulate it as a comparison
between two two
matrices and you can compute something
called the hilit mid distance of the two
matrices and uh you want to see that
distance basically
um getting down to zero ideally as the
agent gets closer and closer to um
making bets according to the quantum the
optimal Quantum
strategy now indeed if you go up to uh
more than 10 to the power of five steps
the agent starts to
approximate um the born rule which is
but that's what you would expect at that
number of steps you're in the regime of
large data um you know that this is like
at that point the agent should be by
construction it should be behaving like
a perfectly rational agent so there's no
surprises there what did surprise us is
that um it it couldn't get such good
performance without such a large amount
of data so it seemed that no matter how
we fiddled with the
parameters um we just couldn't get it to
perform better than
that and this is an open question I mean
whether we could think of more clever
algorithms more sophisticated algorithms
that could get it there but there's a
subtlety because you can't just pick any
algorithm that would give you Optimal
Performance um because your ALG
algorithms doing double duty
uh it's on the one hand it has to be
good at uh detecting the the quantum
effects in the statistics but it also
has to be a plausible
representation of an information
gathering organism that's concerned with
its own Survival and it's that second
point that makes this all
interesting
um because that it's not super well
defined what class of
Agents meet that description
so I I'll just mention um that somewhat
frustratingly we found that even you
know at relatively low numbers of steps
like 500
steps um the value of n like the number
of possible bets the agent can make
doesn't seem to matter much so I
mentioned that earlier on and I guess
that's kind of intuitive um because
realistically when we make bets we don't
make bets of uh you know values below
one cent you know like all our our
decimal places all terminate at two when
it comes to placing bets unless you're
using Bitcoin but let's not talk about
that you know
um you know so the the idea is it's
natural to have a kind of coar graining
of your your U bets AKA probabilities
for the rational agent uh and and that
shouldn't really matter as long as
they're they're find grained
enough um and indeed they don't that
something that was more of a surprise is
that Epsilon doesn't matter at at
relatively low step counts you can see
why at very
large uh data sets Epsilon shouldn't
matter remember Epsilon is the
probability for exploration trying new
things um the reason is that as long as
you have some nonzero
Epsilon when you run
enough
steps that will be sufficient for the
agent to explore the whole Space of
possible actions many
times um so you would you would expect
that for a sufficiently large data
Epsilon should stop being
important um but we didn't quite expect
that it would stop being important so
soon um so that's kind of interesting
but what the upshot of this mean is just
that the main limiting factor on the
agent's performance turned out to be um
just the amount of data itself just the
sheer amount number of
steps um so the lesson that we drew from
that is that unless the agent could
afford the time and energy needed to
acquire this much
data um you know and think 10 to the
five steps depending you know what field
of science you're coming from that may
or may not seem like a large number um
but you know if you think of things that
an organism has to do in order to you
know to take an action and get a
response from the world you know eat eat
a piece of fruit and see if it kills you
or not you know that kind of thing 10 to
the five is pretty
demanding um and so you
know if we Grant the 10 to the five is a
um unfeasibly large number uh for a t a
typical you know a reasonable model of
an agent um then we would have to
conclude that it's just not going to
learn to behave in a manner that
reflects uh the finer Quantum structure
of its environment even when that
environment is explicitly quite strongly
Quantum and this was surprising to us uh
we we really didn't expect
that now it's difficult to draw a
definitive conclusion from
this um but we are tempted to say
something like the following um in
inspired by there's some work by
cognitive scientist Donald
Hoffman some of you might might know of
it who he argues that in
general uh there's a selection pressure
against organisms evolving to perceive
the world as it is
truly um that in fact organisms which
are too accurate in their perceptions of
the world will be um selected out uh
it's just not not an Adaptive Advantage
um and he he argues essentially that
true information is not necessarily
useful information that what we're
evolved to perceive should definitely
not be expected to be what's true but
rather what's relevant to our survival
and that made us Wonder um you know we
pose the following question based on
these preliminary
results could it be that um could
Quantum sensitive Behavior ever be
beneficial to an organism survival
or is it just too hard to
learn um you know if we could make more
formal and well- defined and rigorous
definitions of these terms this would be
a really interesting question to answer
uh the problem is that to really decide
the issue it seems that we need a
generally accepted criteria for what we
mean by life and what we mean by
viability of an organism that would then
constrain the space of of allowed agent
models you know as I said there's a
subtlety in making sure that you're not
just picking an optimal model from a
performance point of view but choosing a
model that uh
plausibly represents uh an actual living
agent and as I said our model in some
ways it's too constrained uh because our
algorithm is so simplistic you might
think that there might be algorithms
which are still realistic models of
Agents but which might perform better
because they just have more uh more more
possible decision- making Machinery
available to them but in other ways our
model is not really constrained enough
uh because as I said we're we're
assuming ideal
measurements uh and and so on so a more
General approach is needed to be
decisive um our preliminary results are
suggestive but I wouldn't say they're
conclusive
so this is the conjecture just to put it
up on the screen even if quantum effects
are strong in the environment Quantum
sensitive life is generally selected
against by survival pressures I.E is not
viable in other words maybe conjecture
maybe the only route to Quantum
sensitive behavior is via higher order
cognition like us you know we humans you
know we're building quantum computers
we're definitely behaving in a way
that's sensitive to Quantum Mechanics
but that's through explicit
reasoning um the conjecture is that
there's no shortcut uh that there's no
way a Mindless agent could evolve
adaptively to become sensitive to
Quantum effects at the behavioral level
um just through
Evolution uh somehow you know knowing
quantum mechanics has to be like an
accident of cognition a bit like
appreciating music
um I mean it's a pipe dream I don't know
if we'll ever be able to resolve this
conjecture but I put it there to
stimulate
discussion so thanks again for listening
and uh I'll open for
questions thank you perhaps
John if you'd like to give a first
comment and then Ander
welcome sure um thanks Jack uh I think
you pretty much covered all the bases um
and somehow I feel like I learned a
little bit about our paper just heing
you sketch it just now even though you
know I'm one of the authors uh but yeah
maybe I'll just reiterate a few of the
things you said um because are maybe the
points that I think are most important
to to really take away because there's a
lot of sort of quantum detail in here
that doesn't matter for the kind of
conclusion that we want to talk about
maybe um and so I guess the main thing
is that if you really had an ideal
basian agent well they would do what
they do also you teach them quantum
mechanics and then they behave in a
certain way the key then ultimately is
that behavior what we want to figure out
is whether there could be a shortcut
right so we came to cubism um from the
idea that decision Theory uh can explain
the born rule like you said in our
previous paper but um real agents are
part of the world they're not ideal they
are
limited and so you know the question is
whether there's a shortcut to the same
behavior so that from the outside it's
sort of approximately indistinguishable
from an ideal basing agent and again we
thought it was really cool that uh you
know you can model things like an ant
colony as a basing agent even though of
course it's not writing down
probabilities and utility and maximizing
expected utility and all of those things
it's just that it takes behaviors that
are sort of indistinguishable from that
whole General
process um so if there were a shortcut
then um then you don't really need
full-blown basian agent concept right
that would be the idea so and then okay
so that that's that's the motivation as
jacqu already covered I'm not really
saying anything new um but we came at
this in just the the very first order
kind of way I think because what we did
was we took the basian agent concept and
weakened it in pretty much the weakest
way that you could weaken it uh we have
agents here that are making bets they
don't know probability Theory but it's
very thinly veiled like there's we we
basically arrange so that in the
infinite data and continuous limit then
their bets are probabilities full stop
um and in order to be coherent they need
to obey probability Theory and they need
to obey the born Rule and that infinite
data would just inevitably lead them
there and indeed we do get there when we
get enough data um but if it had been
the case that sort of a low amount of
exposure to their environment allowed
them to get pretty close to the born
rule that would have made us think okay
well uh maybe the the whole idea of
these higher order thinking beings that
kind of can Implement something like
basian decision Theory and hbert spaces
and so forth that's Overkill and what
you really get you can really get all of
this behaviorally and what actually
matters just from a simple agent-based
model um and we found the opposite
basically we found that it took a lot of
data and a lot of Jerry rigging and
helping and idealizations and you know
simulating things without noise or
anything like that before we can
actually get the agent to behave in a
way that is close enough to the born
rule to be
meaningful um so that is some evidence
as jock said in the direction of well
maybe we really do need these higher
order agents that uh have to use basing
decision Theory and actually you know
think in abstract and so forth but it's
also I I I think we shouldn't forget
that it's it's definitely possible in
fact maybe even likely that we didn't
weaken the basian agent framework idea
enough in our
simulation um and I say that because you
know the bets here are sort of different
probability values uh what if we had
something far more heuristic um and it's
hard for me to think about how we would
actually compare it to the real born
rule in that case but um but I don't
we've certainly not ruled out the
possibility that uh a different kind of
simple agent model um could effectively
learn to behave in a way that aligns
with with quantum theory um with lower
resource cost um in this in the way we
we did generalize it it's sort of the
the goalpost is still you get everything
that you get in the basing agent setting
um and so maybe by definition it
requires a lot of resources to to win
that game it's not clear but anyway way
those are pretty much my my comments uh
and
yeah awesome thank you thank you Andrew
for joining would you like to give an
initial comment and then I'll read any
questions so then we'll continue the
discussion yeah I'm not really in a
position to uh comment much because I
didn't get to read the paper but it was
a very interesting talk the one thing I
want to ask is could you show the slide
on the dchb
again uh that's around the time I showed
up I
think and
then yeah was it the a couple slides
later or was it this one this one maybe
a bit later yeah yeah yeah here we Rec
what was going on here because it
reminded me of something else uh that
we've seen with Chris Fields Daniel but
I I think I missed the explanation so um
it reminds me of contextuality right in
in in in Chris's work like but I might
be messing it up I didn't I didn't hear
an entire
explanation do do you want to know uh
how does how do we use a Dutch book here
like what role is it playing is that
what you're asking yeah no I sort of got
it right I think I think um any one
uh decision
here on its own would you know you could
you could approach optimality right but
when you start taking into account
several possibilities that's when you
have the the dasb phenomenon is that is
that
right yeah uh I I think so if I
understood you right um basically it's
um if you anytime you have an agent who
has a set of
beliefs um you know expressed as
probability assignments to some set of
events that they're concerned with then
there's always going to be a question of
whether those those different
um
uh constraints so so the they beliefs
will generally be expressed as some
constraint on their probability
assignments right and they might have a
bunch of constraints and you want to
make sure that those are all consistent
with each other so the Dutch book is is
just mathematically a really nice way of
testing that
um basically if you can find the Dutch
book using the the agent own probability
assignments that means that their set of
beliefs like the set of constraints that
they're trying to uh adhere to are
mutually in
inconsistent did I did I explain it well
John uh yeah that's that's true I think
um one other thing to point out here
maybe that uh Ander might be asking
about is um so the two things you've
said you you've emphasized here
essentially well actually you only
really emphasized one of them but in
general the Dutch book idea is like a
logical consistency between the
different beliefs that you have and um
like for instance if I said there's a
60% chance it's going to rain today and
a 50% chance it won't rain today well I
can't hold both of those beliefs and the
idea of a Dutch book is that I could ask
you to pay a certain amount for one
ticket that would pay the dollar if it
Reigns and a certain amount for a ticket
that would not that would pay you know
50 cents if it doesn't rain and then you
just lose money for sure the Dutch book
idea is You're vulnerable to a sure loss
um so that's a purely logical constraint
on your beliefs um but the idea that was
motivating this previous work was that
what if that's you have that of course
being consistent is important but you
also perhaps need to be consistent with
some particular kind of characteristic
of the physical world so there's a sort
of coherence that's imposed logically
and a coherence that's imposed
physically um and in the context of
informationally complete measurements
just consider a single measurement and
just your probability for that well
logically the only constraint there is
that you have a probability simplex and
you don't assign something like
probability
110% to to some event or below zero okay
so it has to be between Zer and one
inclusive but for an informationally
complete measurement um physically we
just know this
empirically uh quantum mechanics implies
a restriction of the probabilities that
are valid for full stop for the
assignment for a minimal informationally
complete um measurement and so Quantum
State space the the set of Val Quantum
States you can have corresponds to a
proper subset
of a big informationally complete
probability Simplex um so that's another
kind of um uh consistency you need to
keep in mind if you want to actually be
consistent with logic and with sort of
physics in the
world I see thank you yeah
so I think I think I sort of get it and
and it the point is well taken right
because um the whole I don't know if you
guys are aware of the course that
happened last year but one of the things
that Chris mentioned with uh the quantum
framework of active inference is that
you have this this idea of contextuality
which happens whenever you have
non-commuting qrfs the quantum reference
trins which is you know what an active
inference agent deploys to perform
measurements and actions and whenever
you have uh non-commuting qrfs deployed
you cannot I think basically the idea is
that you cannot have well- defined joint
probability on on the on the boundary uh
so it's morally very related but I will
have to check the details but thank you
guys um actually now now I I get what
you're aiming at yeah I it's it's not
just morally related I think it it is um
the same thing or or closely related
like formly because actually the way
that that um our co-author on the paper
Blake Stacy put it is that it's an
assumption of no hidden
variables um which amounts to
contextuality basically saying that you
uh there can't be a joint probability
distribution I mean let me let me try to
say something that is both precise and
probably correct if if you believe that
you're dealing with a contextual
phenomenon you know that that you have
measurements which are non-commuting in
in the relevant sense then I think you
would need to have something like our
assumption
to there is although I'm not sure the it
would give you in quantum theory it
would then two would definitely hold so
this tomographic Dimension is
information dimensional squared because
in quantum theory the the minimal number
of outcomes for an informationally
complete measurement is D SED the
Hilbert space Dimension
squared so but whether if you look in a
more General probabilistic framework if
you have some definition of
contextuality it's not clear to me if
that would give you the squared it would
give you something something like this
so you would definitely I would expect
you to have a non equality here so it
would be non-classical in the sense that
your tomographic dimension should not be
equal to the information Dimension when
you have
contextuality uh proof pending
I bet that that's true I I believe it is
the case that the Assumption of there be
the possibility of a non-contextual
hidden variable model uh is possible to
formulate in terms of these proper
subsets of quantum State space that I
was talking about I mean of of the
informationally complete Simplex that I
was talking about it just so happens
that Quantum State space itself pokes
outside of that and so that means that
in general it's not compatible with the
idea of a non- textual hidden variable
model or to put it more positively if
you want to talk about hidden variables
which we don't personally but if you do
then you have to have a contextual
model well thank you that's very good
awesome okay I'll read some of the
comments in the live chat um and then
I'll I'll have a few things I wrote down
so
um the text a little small but
RV says is the agent always trying to
guess the same Quantum
State um well so first the point of
clarification the
agent isn't really trying to guess a
Quantum State uh they're doing something
much more basic they're just trying to
guess what the outcome of the
measurement will be
um and well they they're trying to guess
the probability for for each outcome is
it a fixed coin flip with a static or
changing probability so I mean those
those probabilities will be different
for different Quantum States uh you know
of that for instance in our
implementation you your environment is
is just a single photon with some
polarization State and that polarization
State depending what it is will give you
different probabilities to get the
outcomes and the answer is yes we do
need to consider different Quantum
States uh the reason is because if you
just hold the quantum State fixed you
your statistics will not be rich enough
to uh to be distinctively Quantum so in
that case you you would be able to
explain those statistics with a
classical model and you would not expect
your agent to be able to learn anything
Quantum in that situation so you need to
have not just several Quantum States but
Quantum states which are
sufficiently varied across state space
um that it that it
[Music]
um yeah but when when an agent when an
agent is trying to learn a certain
probability though we assume that
they're in the same context where they
have the same state and the same
measurement and they repeat that a bunch
of times so that might that might have
been the question I just want to make
sure good point yeah yeah I didn't
clarify
that yeah so the the you know we kind of
the agent is allowed to know like that
it when it's in a different uh
environmental context corresponding to a
different state um so it can you know
put the relevant labels on its um Bing
Behavior awesome very connected with
context switching and attention um I'll
read a question or comment in the chat
Andrew Pasa wrote active agents priors
over observations their preferences
which is what generalizes and includes
the reward maximization in the pragmatic
value and then expected free energy ads
in the epistemic value actin agents
prior over observation their preferences
as survival related homeostats expected
free energy drops the need for defining
an Epsilon for random SL exploratory
Behavior
h i I have difficulty in responding to
that because I'm not
sure how free energy connects with this
but this is something I wanted to
ask uh maybe this is this might be
exactly the kind of reason why we need
to talk with you guys because I didn't
even understand the question but clearly
you're coming from a a background that
um uh knows more about the agent
modeling side of things than we
do let let me pull back and just a few
of the things that I wrote cuz there's
kind of a a a triple intersection that
that's funny and and led to to this
through citation LS Etc so kind of from
how I understood the journey and the the
the generalization SL weakening but
experimentally designed and the
constraints of of the real experimental
setup and the more generic equations and
also weakening those or figuring out how
they could change so you set out from
the quantum born across the real
experimental interfaces and got to some
of these multiscale possibly adaptive
Dynamics like reward surprise Fitness
that are tological
about
situations then in octave inference
there's kind of a a dual origin which is
like one of the figures in chapter 1 of
the 2022 textbook with this idea of
active inference in the middle or coming
from or two the low road and the high
road so the low road is like the
generalized sensory motor Loop so kind
of like cybernetics or with the embodied
connection like robotics or embodiment
and then also the high road is the
basian mechanics free energy principle
principle of least action for basian all
of those kinds of things so those are
the first two threads with the quantum
born empirical setting then the active
inference kind of well there is this
sequentiality to behavioral updating on
the inbound sensory and on the outbound
action which is like selecting a bet is
like an action and chrisfield takes that
into the quantum fvp which is like more
of a recent development and then the
third element is like the ant infer ant
which was the paper from
20121 so lot to say about ants but the
colony for anal Iz ing The Colony as a
phenomena it it highlights and it starts
from the lateral interactions amongst
nestmates like the collective Behavior
and the interactions with the niche
including like different kinds of
pheromone Decay or something like that
like a sunny context might have a higher
rate of Decay and then also there's this
kind of pragmatism of measuring anything
which you have in the laboratory in the
quantum setting and then also also
there's that experimental constraint in
the laboratory for ants and also in the
field for ants so it's kind of like the
pragmatism and the real finite
constraint and kind of our experimental
reality and then it's just interesting
that you came at this from the best
experimental and
updating process about systems that that
many might say are non-cognitive or sub
cognitive or something like that or just
differently and then also but from the
more generalized cognitive side that has
led into Quantum Baye whether or not
there's like a
mechanistically Quantum effect in the
brain that doesn't mean that the
decision Theory isn't already
transferable what do you think orot in
there I'm busy absolving that
yeah you know you mentioned I mean one
of the things about this work on on
active inference is the multiscale
structure and this was something that in
our paper we kind of handwave towards
the
end uh about
our work really focusing on I guess what
you were calling the low road which in
the sense that we we thought of our
little Proto agent as more like an
ant um but then we we kind of posed the
question of whether if you got a lot of
these guys together and had them
interacting or or somehow working
together you could uh kind of look at
the whole system and get an emergent
Behavior which you to which you could
attribute uh you could model from from a
kind of
basian rational agent point of view um
but that you know we didn't really get
as far is addressing the the kind of
multiscale stuff I think because we
we're still trying to work out the
fundamentals you know pure action
response Dynamics I mean maybe we need
the multiscale thing in order to
meaningfully generalize or to weaken
like that might be the the right thing
to do um and it may maybe make sense
that uh it's so hard
to uh make a simplified sort of
non-cognitive approximation of the
basian agent model in the way that we
did but you know we did it this way
because we didn't know any better
essentially well yeah it's it's it's
awesome two of the things from Chris
fields's course the physics as
information processing was also relaxing
sometimes constraints about space and
time like having agents make their own
spatial temporal reference frames so
rather than just plugging in agents into
kind of a grid work that's defined by an
observer whether or not they're modeling
themselves um and then also just the the
environments and the partition the
interface the blanket all those
different ways to describe the interface
between internal and external States or
what whatever notation or variables are
used so that's kind of like the
communication setting like Alice and Bob
but then maybe Bob is the ground and its
ferone distributions as actions but then
it's not about like whether or not
that's like an action of the ground it's
like well that's being modeled by a
person making another finite model so
it's a map territory for how they're
drawing
it so there's a lot of interesting
pieces
and great great topics to go into
yeah one other connection is you said
something about General born extending
into the unobservables and this is like
one of the key moves with the separation
of observations and latent or hidden or
external States so there's like a the
ambiguity Matrix which is just a
bidirectional mapping what would the
measurement distribution be from a
hidden State what does this
observation and then the observations
can be attached with epistemic value and
a pragmatic value value related to like
the cost of sampling and just the
preferences against expected future
observations those are all kind of like
cognitive motifs like we could
explore what experiments do or do not
show that a nestmate
plans can you falsify or put a
probability distribution over the idea
that it's doing something Beyond its
immediate sensory blanket how many time
steps of memory how many time steps of
anticipation that's a model selection
question with a certain labber field
data set it's like well there's there
could be a difference but it would
require getting 10 to the five foraging
runs by the same nest M but it may never
take that many and so that also kind of
tucks back into the evolutionary
priors and the distributional starting
position which is like always a problem
in applying basian statistics and then
there's like a kind of neat Fitness
oriented way to give the prior
yeah I I mean and and also I mean use
the nest mate language which is a fun
fun thing to talk about uh I mean in our
s like one single ant alone is pretty
useless because it can never live long
enough to get 10 to the five things but
if it's got a bunch of nestates and they
can communicate with their phermones and
so forth then maybe 10 to the five isn't
a lot when you have a bunch of of Agents
interacting and so
forth It's it's a great interesting
debate with the ant colony world and
what's interesting about ants I mean
among things is they're obligately
Colony living whereas other hopin like
even the bees and the Wasps they have a
lot more variability with different life
histories but then the ants have the
obligate us sociality so that kind of
like the termites or different than than
those other ones like in both those or
the any obligately
social
form then the unit of Fitness can be
kind of targeted as and so it sets a
norm not the only possible Norm but it's
like Optimal foraging Theory it's like
is it about one nestmate getting the
most food per unit time it's like maybe
if that were a special special case of
water loss and time and Colony hunger
and the seasonality then it could be
considered optimal but if the optimal
strategy is not then the she amount of
foraging activity or type of it it can't
be considered like it's only optimal
within an evolutionary context otherwise
you're just saying who is foraging
more
right
right this is a bit off topic but I uh
it's a a wild idea that just kind of
popped into my head now that we're
talking about actual organisms like
ants um you know it occurs to me that
most of the
living creatures that we could think of
off the top of our heads so far as we
know uh are
not specifically sensitive to Quantum
effects I know there is a literature on
Quantum effects in biology um but it's
usually really down at the chemical
level like in
photosynthesis um or or uh but you know
I wonder like there's work that you know
the human
eye is it it they know that the the
cells in the retina are sensitive down
to the single Photon level like in
principle just a handful of photons can
trigger a retinal cell fire and there
are experiments kind of working on I
know because my my wife who's also one
of the co-workers on this paper is
working on this stuff here in Brazil um
but uh it makes me wonder if like maybe
there are because there are creatures
out there with some pretty amazing
capabilities like there's the mantis
shrimp which has these crazy that have
trinocular vision and I don't know what
else you know maybe there are some
living creatures that we could actually
get into a controlled lab environment
and have them actually interacting with
uh Quantum stuff you know if they're
Photon sensitive you could kind of see
if you can fire photons at them and get
them to behave in a in a responsive way
I don't know that just seems like it
might be really cool I'm just throwing
that out there what would it like mean
or show if if there was a way to do
it it would just be cool
man that made me think of having the
photon instead of killing a hypothetical
cat it releases one like phermone for a
moth or one molecule of glucose for a
bacteria so and that's kind of what the
synapse does with the discretization
into the packets and then to the
neurotransmitter discretization level
with
release and and that also relates to
something came up a lot in the Chris
Fields was the interplay of of kind of
classical and
non-classical state
spaces and the interface as being like
the more classical
barrier and then different aspects of
that when it's interacting with the
quantum Alice and Quantum
Bob Andre want to add anymore where
where else do you think it would like
connect
yeah that that was an interesting
thought by Ja um but my question to you
is don't you think that the the issue of
Agents being able to observe Quantum
effects
um you know I I see it related to the FP
in the following way like one of the
latest papers he talks about the FP
driving
compartmentalization and you can imagine
that as an organism you know becomes
larger and more s sophisticated they'll
have more degrees of freedom available
to be able to pick up very subtle
Quantum effects and and even more outter
idea you know it almost feels like no
difference to how we need High energies
in
accelerators to observe real small stuff
you
know yeah one one other kind of topic
I'd love to hear more about was the
fourfold nature of the experiment
because that made think about a c a
collision of the particles and how
that's often thought of as like two
interacting
components however there's also like
let's just say that there are two real
interacting real question mark then you
have an interface and then like a s and
an O you have observation and then at
least a measurement frame that's been
learned or calibrated like the a matrix
projecting on to Like A P value or base
fact
some other kind of other further
Downstream um analysis so it's like are
there four things there and then what
are those
four and so what is it about the
fourness of the empirical setup and how
is it exactly two for the exponent or
how does is that variable or is that
always an
integer that too is purely
from Hilbert space geometry and so in so
far as we use quantum theory and well in
so far as the model is
right and according Associated to any
system you can always write down a
Hilbert space of some Dimension then
it's just a matter of mathematical fact
that the state space only spans a d s
well actually d^2 minus one because
there's a normalization but anyway it's
a D2 dimensional operator space which is
where Quantum States live um and so yeah
we can't you can't it can't be d2+ one
or d^2 minus one unless you're talking
about something other than quantum
theory um and so far we don't seem to
have anything other than quantum theory
so that's yeah that that empirical part
I mean we call it empirical but it's
empirical at the level
of is this Theory we've been using for
100 years actually right not empirical
at the well we measured this Mass and it
looks like it's within this and this and
it's plus or minus you know so it's it's
like pretty
solid it's a bit of a lie to call it
it's not purely empirical yeah it's meta
empirical it's it's met empirical and
it's pragmatic in the sense of
pragmatism which isn't uh some kind of
pure utilitarianism but pragmatism just
deals with the pragmatic aspects of of
operations okay yeah like magmatically
if you if you want to do state
tomography you're going to need at least
D Squared outcomes and they better be
good ones yes yeah and then an
interesting extension into the
behavioral space where neither kind of I
mean Mass bace classical models but even
kind of classical inspired models don't
describe all behavioral data and then
like if the observation has
dimensionality n like n sensors for
Sensor Fusion then a has N squared
because it's square or second powered to
to map all the Matrix mapping all by all
observations to Hidden States and then B
which is what the control policy is
exerted as a slice from which is like a
behavioral collapse from makes it
another Power because there's how the
the S Vector changes so a kind of
balloons it out but then projects it
back down to some other possible space
and then B uh it I squares s because
it's a transition
selection and so
then there's a lot of interesting traces
to follow
there I confess that mostly went over my
head but
it's it's not
yeah what about the plus or minus
one which plus or minus one from the d^2
plus or minus one like what what would
it why could it be plus or
minus oh no I was I was saying it
couldn't be oh okay yeah sorry Theory
yeah yeah if if it were different it
would be a different Theory that's what
I'm saying uh yeah so it looks like it
has to be um Des I
mean it's something that would be nice
to explore one day like what what are
these theories that have different
numbers that not just the squared but
uh yeah too too many questions too
little time we're only on a 4D live
stream you
can't um well what happens next
or where should others or what are you
going to explore well I think you know
based on this conversation the thing
that sounds most promising to me if we
were going to take this further is the
multiscale part like I think really we
want to model agents or an agent or the
the the the target of basy an agent has
to
be sort of the emergent property of many
little guys I think that's that's
probably the most pertinent uh thing to
take from your um kind of community and
that what we totally ignored in this
work um and yeah so we didn't yeah we
barely mentioned that in the paper but I
think personally that feels like the
most exciting possible way to push this
direction
further I don't know about jacqu yeah I
think John I think you're probably right
uh just pragmatically speaking it that
seems
like something that's concrete and well
defined enough that that one could
actually make progress in that direction
and it would be
interesting but you know just speaking
from like what what is like the question
that I would really like to know the
answer to but I'm not even sure how to
formulate it in a way that could be
attacked with research is you know
there's this idea that quantum theory is
a bit weird because of this you know
like the non-contextuality thing
um so and we the world that we live in
and that so far as we know all living
creatures live in is not a Quantum world
you know where're macroscopic thermal
completely decoherent creatures know um
decoherent in the sense that quantum
theory just isn't important to our
everyday interactions with our world and
I guess I'm wondering whether that's
just an accident of the fact that life
evolved in in a very hot wet you know
regime where Quantum coherence doesn't
survive or whether there might be a
deeper reason behind it that somehow if
you try tried to create life under
really controlled conditions where you
enabled Quantum coherence to survive and
be like Quantum coherence to be really
strong in the environment you know
imagine like if if Plank's constant were
just some really large value in a
hypothetical Universe could life evolve
in that universe or is there something
about the weirdness of quantum theory
that that forces life to only exist in
in uh effectively in in decoherent
regime
you know that's kind of bit a deep
question I have um I'm sure that our
very preliminary work hasn't shed any
light on it but I think it did do the
valuable job of raising it as a
question yeah I mean because what could
have happened was we could have just
immediately found that even in the first
attempt to weaken the basing agent thing
it just gets the born roll immediately
and then you can say well
probably well but it also would have I
mean you know it it would have said oh
well we're sort of barking up the wrong
tree with this highlevel basy and
decision Theory approach it's not
necessary um so far as we know it is
necessary still uh but um anyway we
didn't rule it out yeah an interesting
thread there it's the paper discussed in
live stream number 49 with ramstead and
stiv devel with showing the kind of
development and generalization of Cl
classical thermodynamic infodynamics
server or interface that being the
basian mechanics which is the where the
path of least action free energy
principle all that is existing and it's
like another generalization from the
it's another degree of Freedom which is
the analytic aspect and the
pragmatically constrained reality of it
for the quantum
investigator so you're doing it so
that's
cool we're on the path we're doing
something yeah well any last comments
for
anyone uh read the
paper read the paper it's a classic
it otherwise yeah maybe it be a classic
yeah
um looking forward to it we'll be happy
to stay in touch and Ander and others
and Chris fields we could explore a lot
more yeah and the measurement and the
quantum and we can explore with the ant
multi-agent Frameworks so there's a lot
of great paths I think I think jacqu and
I need to read up on that and then we'll
come back to you that seems like seems
promising to me yeah okay thank you
thanks for having us bye thanks for
having us